Friends make life good.
友人は人生をいいものにする
They provide the  scaffolding that makes it not just bearable but fun.
人生の困難に耐え、楽しむ土台になるのだ
They give us a sense of meaning  and purpose and are a source of security, self esteem and happiness.
友人は生きる意味と目的を与え
安心感、自尊心、幸福感の源になる
Almost nothing predicts how happy you will be as how connected you feel
幸福度の指標として
「つながり」は最重要で
and a lack of social connection is associated with a number of diseases and a shorter life.
社会的な孤立は
多くの病気や寿命の短さにつながる
But maybe you have scrolled through your phone,  unsure who to call to go to a movie with, to celebrate with or ask for comfort.
でも誰を誘えばいいのかわからない
映画、お祝い、慰めの相手に
You may realize that you don’t have enough friends and feel lonely.
友人の少なさに孤独を感じるかも
And it is not just you.
あなただけじゃない
Disconnectedness and loneliness are widespread.
断絶と孤独は蔓延している
Many people want more close friends  but don’t know how to get them.
多くが友人を欲するが
作り方がわからない
Surprisingly nowadays loneliness is highest among  young people – whose relationships were also hit especially hard by the global pandemic.
意外にも若い層が最も孤独で
彼らの人間関係はパンデミックで大打撃を受けた
Social distancing stopped teens and young adults from mingling in classrooms, clubs or dorms.
社会的距離は教室、クラブ、寮での交流を阻んだ
Millions  of friendships, maybe lifelong friendships, that might have blossomed will never exist.
大量の交友関係が
成立前に芽を摘まれた
With profound long term consequences for our collective happiness.
これは長期的な幸福の総量を大きく変える
The good news is that it is not too  late and there are lots of friends to be found.
ここで朗報だ
手遅れじゃない、友人の候補はたくさんいる
We’ll mix scientific information  with actionable advice in this video,
ここから、科学的情報と助言を織り交ぜていくが
but we can’t address every individual situation.
個別の状況には対応できない
People, cultures and schedules are different.
人も、文化も、日程も違うのだ
If you suffer from chronic loneliness you  can also watch the video we made about it.
慢性的な孤独感に悩んでいるなら
関連動画もどうぞ
Ok. As with all important things in life, making friends is infuriatingly simple but not necessarily easy.
さて、他の人生の重要事項と同様
友人作りはごく単純だが、必ずしも容易ではない
But it works through a few pretty straight forward mechanisms.
少数の、ごく単純な仕組みだ
The Most Important Thing about Making Friends
【友人作りの最重要事項】
People make friends with other people  when they spend casual time together.
何気ない時間を共に過ごすことで
友人はできる
This is how our ancestors formed their  relationships,
これは祖先の関係づくりと同じで
because humans lived in small, close knit communities in which  options for making friends were limited,
閉鎖的な小集団での生活は
友人の選択肢も乏しかった
so we just formed good relationships  with the people who were around us.
だから身近な人間と良好な関係を築くのだ
This is why it is so easy to form new friendships in school and university.
学校や大学での友人作りが容易なのも同じことで
Society locks you and your peers in a building for several years.
同じ場所に数年も閉じ込めてくれる
You share similar activities but more importantly:
Similar schedules.
活動内容も、何よりスケジュールも同様だ
Overlapping  and fluctuating social circles form naturally giving you regular facetime
生活圏が重なることで
日頃から顔を合わせることになり
and  shared experiences with many different people.
様々な人と経験を分かち合う
Time to find others with similar
worldviews or senses of humor.
共通の価値観、ユーモアの持ち主と出会う機会だ
Proximity can be more important than similar interests.
共通の関心より
身近さが重要な場合もある
One study found that in student dormitories, the distance between rooms was the  strongest friendship predictor
寮の友人関係は部屋の近さと
最も強く関係していたという研究もある
– living closer together meant a higher chance of becoming friends.
部屋が近いほど
友人になる機会が多いのだ
Another study showed that being physically present in a class a lot, without saying a word, makes others more sympathetic to you.
教室に居さえすれば、仮に無言でも
周囲がより共感的になるという研究もある
So the most important principle of making friends is to regularly spend time with people in the real world.
友人作りの最重要原則は
実世界で定期的に他人と過ごすことなのだ
This alone can make it happen automatically and trumps all other advice.
これだけで友達ができることもあり
残りの助言に勝る
But don’t forget that making friends  is not a numbers game or a competition,
ただ、友人作りは数字遊びや競争ではない
don’t compare yourself to others.
周囲と比べないように
Everyone  has a social calibrator that can change as  you go through life.
社会性は、生きるうちに変化していくものだ
Maybe you were  more introverted as a teen
10代では内向的だったが
but yearn for connection in your twenties.
20代では繋がりに憧れるかも
Maybe you were part of sprawling social circles
but prefer fewer friends in your thirties.
30代では広い交友の輪を離れ
少人数の輪を好むかも
There is no right or wrong, only right for you.
いいも悪いもなく
個人的な正解があるだけだ
Why we don’t have enough friends
【友達が足りない理由】
The main reason for a lack of friendships is the trite fact that most people do not  prioritize friendships nearly enough.
交友関係が希薄になる理由は陳腐で
ほとんどの人が重視していないからだ
They don’t realize until it is too late, that retaining friendships demands regular energy and attention.
日頃から気にかけないと交友関係は維持できないと
手遅れになって気づく
Although they are so important for happiness, friends often take a backseat to other life decisions.
幸福において重要な存在なのに
友人は後回しにされがちだ
Work, commuting, romance or kids take up so much time and energy
仕事、通勤、恋愛、子育てが時間と体力を奪い
that it is so much easier to crash on your couch and lose yourself in mindless activities.
ソファーに身を投げ出し
ダラダラしたくもなる
Especially as an adult, going for a bike ride, getting dinner or visiting a hobby store takes much more mental effort and commitment
自転車をこいだり、外食に行ったりするのに
大人は気力が必要だ
than it did after school, when time ran slower and energy and curiosity were abundant.
エネルギーと好奇心にあふれ、
時間がゆっくりだった頃とは違うのだ
But it is not just adults who  are too busy for friends.
でも忙しいのは大人だけじゃない
The average American teenager spends  more time on Tik Tok every day,
アメリカのティーンはTikTokに熱心だ
than socializing at parties, events  or on the phone with friends combined.
パーティーやイベント、電話で友人と交流するよりも
Established friendships don't require the  same time investment as early friendships to keep up
友情が確立すれば
あまり時間をかけずに維持できる
– but they do require some commitment.
だが、気に掛ける必要はあるのだ
As life distracts you, it’s easy to skip out on checking in when a friend goes through exciting or depressing times.
日常に追われると、友人の興奮や落ち込みを
ついスルーしてしまう
And so many friendships fade for  lack of attention, often by accident.
多くの友情が
偶然の注意不足で薄れていくのだ
Which is extra tragic because there is never only one person losing a friend.
さらに悲劇なのは
友人を失うのは１人だけじゃなく
It’s always at least two.
少なくとも２人以上だ
Another thing that makes many people vulnerable  is the way friendship networks are structured.
孤独になりがちな要因は
交友関係の作られ方にもある
The friendship paradox is the phenomenon that  on average, most people have fewer friends than their friends.
平均的にみると自分より友人の方が交友が広い
友情のパラドックスだ
Which makes sense, since you are more likely to be friends with someone who has many friends, than with someone who has few.
交友関係が広い人ほど
自分と友人になる確率も高いからだ
Rather than being densely interconnected, friend networks are often built around central hubs.
個々人の繋がりというより
交友関係は中心人物の周囲にできるものだ
So if central people disappear from your life, this can deprive you of many connections at once.
だから中心人物と疎遠になると
多くの交友が一度に失われうる
And it can lead to a distorted self perception:
これは自己認識を歪めるかも
that you are less popular than others, although you are perfectly average.
実際はごく普通でも
友人が少ないと感じるのだ
It can get worse quickly with big life  events.
人生の転機では一気に悪化しうる
Maybe you moved for school, work or love and are left without social networks.
進学、就職、結婚に伴い引っ越すと
交友関係から孤立する
Or you had a break up that left you with the smaller  part of the formerly shared social pie.
あるいは以前の関係と決別し
交流の一部だけが残っているかも
The reasons why you find yourself with less connection than you want are as diverse as people,
自分が孤独だと感じる理由は
人それぞれだが
but the underlying cause is almost always:
概ね、根本的な原因は－
Time.
時間だ
There is no shortcut.
近道はない
To make new friends and retain friendships
友人を作り、維持するには
you have to prioritize relationships, spend time with people  in real life and make them feel that you care.
友情の優先度を上げ、共に時間を過ごし
関心を示す必要がある
So take a look at yourself and rebalance what you spend your life doing.
自身を振り返り、人生の時間配分を見直そう
How to make new Friends
【新たな友人の作り方】
Studies have shown that new friendships can  develop quite quickly, weeks after you meet someone.
研究によると、新たな友情は
出会って数週という早期に形成される
But it takes a few months for a casual  friendship to become a close relationship
だが、友人が親友になるには
数ヶ月が必要で
– with the biggest impediment being time invested  and the quality of your interactions.
投資した時間と交流の質が
最大の壁になる
To make friends it helps if you  intentionally look for people
you have things in common with and  who are open to new relationships.
共通項のある人や社交的な人を
意図的に探すなら、友人を作る助けになる
You want to make it easy for yourself, so examine  what kind of person you are.
これを楽に実行したいなら
自分を知ることだ
Generally speaking, extroverts tend to crave sensory stimulation,
一般に、外向的な人は感覚的な刺激を求める
spicier foods, loud music, or the excitement of engaging a crowd.
辛口な食事、大音量の音楽
観客を集める興奮など
Introverts, often confused with shy people, tend to be more sensitive to sensory stimulants
内向的な人は、感覚的な刺激に
敏感な傾向にあり
and prefer quieter surroundings,  fewer people and even less spicy food.
静かな環境、少人数を好み
辛口を好まない人すらいる
Different places attract different people.
人によって好む場所は違う
Not everybody can easily make friends at a bar or a football game,
バーやサッカー観戦での交流に向かない人
not everybody finds a stroll through a park or book
store stimulating.
公園や本屋の散歩に刺激を感じない人もいる
Men especially form  friendships around shared activities
男性は特に共同作業がオススメだが
but in general it is a good idea to  go to places that feel comfortable,
where there are people you might like,  who do things you find interesting.
居心地の良い場所に行き、面白いことをしている
好ましい人と出会うのもいいだろう
Look for local clubs or opportunities to volunteer.
地域の集まり、ボランティアなどもいい
Check out what hobby stores are around and dust off your Space Marines,
近隣の模型店を調べ
オモチャを引っ張りだしたり
or  see if there are new DnD groups in your city and ask if you could join one.
新たなTRPGの集まりがあれば加入したり
Check meet  up apps for gaming nights or wine tasting, join a sports club or look for people  who go hiking or want to cook together.
ゲーム会、試飲会、スポーツ、ハイキング、料理会を
meet upで見つけ、参加しよう
Another obvious avenue is your professional life.
もう一つの明確な道は
職業生活にある
It helps if you work in a job that attracts  people you like, so you might consider this when you choose a career.
好感の持てる人が集まる職種なのか
就活で考慮するのもいいだろう
Deepening your  relationship with colleagues can lead to great friendships,
関係を深めた同僚は
良き友人になりうる
especially if you look for peers and there is no power imbalance.
相手が対等な同期なら、尚更だ
And of course there are friends you’ve lost touch with.
それに、疎遠になった友人もいる
You may be able to revive some of these relationships.
関係を復旧できるかもしれない
In some cases all it needs is a call or an invitation.
電話や誘いだけで十分な場合もある
Research shows that more often than not, the other person  will appreciate that you’ve reached out!
こういった連絡は
高確率で感謝されることがわかっている
There are likely way more opportunities to spend time with others than you are aware of.
誰かと過ごすチャンスは
想像以上に多いはずだが
And if there aren’t, you can take the initiative and  create them.
不十分なら
あなたがチャンスを作ることができる
Invitations are signals to start friendships.
招待は交友開始の合図だ
So bring people together by having a dinner party, organizing a football game after work or starting a board game group.
夕食会、終業後のサッカー
ボードゲームの集団づくりなどで、人を集めよう
Everybody  appreciates people who organize fun things
楽しい機会を作れば感謝される
and the simple act of reaching out can kickstart a  self propelling upward spiral of well being,fun and connectedness
ちょっとした行動で、幸福度、楽しさ、繋がりが
高まる好循環を始められる
that can seriously improve the  life of everyone around you in meaningful ways.
あなたの周りの人生も
有意義な形で向上する
If you meet someone you vibe with it is pretty  scary to make the first move
誰かに好感を持った時
第一歩には勇気がいるが
but they may feel the same way.
相手も同じかも
Equally interested in a friendship  but also blocked by fear of rejection.
お互いに交友を望みつつ
踏み出せないのかもしれない
So it is worth going for it.
だから踏み出そう
Worst case, they are not interested which will sting for a few hours
最悪の場合、数時間を浪費するが
– but the best case could be a lifelong friendship.
生涯の友人ができるかも
A risk well worth the reward.
報酬はリスクより
格段に大きい
Once you have formed early connections check in when they have important things happening in their life.
交流が始まったら
相手の人生の重要な出来事に注視しよう
Of course it is important not to be overbearing
もちろん、重たくない範囲で
but the more time you invest, the more opportunity you have to engage in meaningful banter or silly jokes.
時間をかけるほど
有意義な雑談、他愛ない冗談の機会は増える
The fact that friendships take time also means that you need to be patient  and kind with yourself,
友情には時間が必要だ
無理はせず辛抱強くいこう
especially if you are out of practice.
特に、慣れないうちは
Things will not improve overnight but slowly, step by step, if you keep it up.
継続すれば、一歩一歩ゆっくりと改善されていく
Open Up: Care and Share
【心を開く：ケアとシェア】
Many people don’t have an issue being around others but struggle to turn acquaintances into friends.
他者と過ごすのは苦にならないが
友達作りには苦戦するという人が多い
So let us talk about two important principles  that make it more likely that you’ll connect:
そこで交流を促進する
２大原則を紹介しよう
Caring and sharing.
ケアとシェアだ
In general, our favorite  topic is ourselves and the things we care about,
人は、自分自身や自分の関心事の話題が好きだ
because we are literally at the center of our own universe.
主観的には宇宙の中心にいるのだから
So People tend to like people who are genuinely interested  in them.
だから、自分に興味がある人を好む傾向にある
So if you want to make friends, your goal should be trying to  learn what makes them tick.
友達を作るには
他者の行動原理を知ろうとすべきだ
Just as important as caring about others  is reciprocity and openness.
ケアに劣らず重要なのが、自己開示だ
To connect you need to share the experiences that made you, you.
交流では、あなたを形成した出来事をシェアすべきだ
Now you don’t want to overwhelm the other person and immediately spill out  your deepest secrets.
ここで、唐突に自分をさらけ出すのはやりすぎで
But open up a little and reveal personal things
秘密を少し開示すればいい
– because this  also signals to others that it is ok to do the same.
相手も自己開示がしやすくなる
The best case is that you find shared experiences
最善のケースでは
共通の経験が見つかる
– maybe you both had a hard time in school,
学校での困難な時間とか
maybe you share a passion for weird movies.
奇妙な映画への情熱とか
Learning about others and sharing personal  stories in a
balanced way and not overdoing it, is not an exact science.
相手を知り、個人的な物語を共有するのだが
その匙加減に厳密な正解はない
Noticing the  line between opening up and oversharing requires
practice and depends  on the vibe of the conversation.
自己開示の適切な度合いを見極めるには経験が必要で
会話の雰囲気にも依存する
One of the perplexities of life is that to get something, it can be helpful to convince yourself  that you want it less than you do.
ややこしいことに、何かを得たいときには
「そこまで欲しくない」という自己暗示が有効だ
In general it is good to be laid back, have fun and enjoy yourself.
リラックスして楽しみ、
自分らしくいたほうがいい
Do things for yourself without expectations,
期待せずに自分らしく行動し
but also be open to social opportunities
交流の機会にオープンでいて
and accept invitations if they show up.
誘いがあれば受け入れる
And that's basically it.
基本的にそれだけだ
Give friendships more priority in your life.
交友関係の優先順位を上げること
Check in with friends and regularly go to things to have fun.
友人と連絡を取り合い
定期的に遊びに行く
Show genuine interest  in others and give them the opportunity to know you without selling yourself too  hard.
他者に純粋な興味を示し
適度に自分を知ってもらう機会を作る
If you do this you are on track.
実行できれば成功は近い
If this sounds a bit scary, the good news is that human brains are hardwired to seek connection.
少し怖いなら、いい知らせがある
人間の脳は結びつきを強く求めるものだ
It is perfectly normal to seek out new friends and there
are many people who would welcome more close relationships.
友人を求めるのは当然だし
親密な関係を歓迎する人は多い
There are friendships up for grabs everywhere
友情の種はそこら中にあり
and there are plenty of people who will be so happy  to have YOU in their life.
あなたのいる人生を喜んでくれる人は
たくさんいるのだ
As a good friend. Go get to know them!
良き友人として、手を伸ばそう
For a short time, there is a free, community  organized, world wide Kurzgesagt meetup!
少しの間、Kurzgesagt公式のmeet upを
無料公開します！
If you are over 18 and want to take part:
18歳以上はぜひご参加を
go to  our temporary subreddit that our community set up for you
期間限定の公式subredditを訪れ
and look for your area or city, to find a Kurzgesagt meet up near you.
最寄りのKurzgesagt meet upを見つけましょう
If there isn’t one, don’t be shy- set  it up yourself to meet like minded people.
自分の地域が無ければ
思い切って自分で設定し、気の合う人と会いましょう
In order to make this less intimidating,
we’ve created a small toolbox for you,
気軽な利用のため
ツールボックスも作りました
with some guidance and ideas on what you could  do and
where you could meet up, as well as conversation starters.
できること、会える場所、話の切り出し方について
提案と案内があります
Check out the website  or subreddit for further information and tips!
詳細やヒントは
公式サイトやsubredditで
Please note that this is an experiment, it is free
and self organized by Kurzgesagt viewers like you.
これは実験であり、あなたのようなKurzgesagt視聴者が
自主的に無料で行うものです
The subreddit will be open for  3 weeks and will be made private after.
このsubredditは３週間公開され
その後はプライベート化します
We want to create more things to  make finding friends easier for you,
友人探しを助けるものを
さらに作る予定で
you can also sign up so we can let you know as soon as something is ready!
ご登録いただければ
準備が整い次第お知らせできます
We want to be part of your friendship journey, so we’ve
created a few things you can share with new and old friends!
あなたの友人づくりの旅に寄り添うため
新旧の友人とシェアできるものを作りました
Two wormhole pins to connect you and your BFF  no matter where you are.
２つのワームホールピンは
一番の大親友と常につなげてくれます
If you want to share something with your entire friend group – get a  little bird pin for each of them.
友人グループ全体へのシェアなら
小鳥のピンを全員に配りましょう
They are all unique but fit together like pieces of a puzzle.
同じものはなく、パズルのように繋がります
Or get matching posters to let your friends know  you’re thinking of them.
あるいはつながるポスターで
気にかけていると示すか
Or just browse all the sciency things we made for you!
あるいは科学グッズをただ眺めるか
If you like videos like this, getting something from our shop is the  best way to support us!
このような動画が好きなら
ショップでのご購入が最良のサポートです
Thank you for watching.
ご視聴ありがとうございました